http://youtu.be/9xRmNLc7ZOo
khang_vgu
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: The essence of the universal receiver transmitter
DR. JONATHAN: bản chất của bộ thu và bộ phát universal là data được gửi nối tiếp nhau
is that the data is sent serially.
...
That means one bit at a time.
nghĩa là chỉ 1 bit tại 1 thời điểm
The idle condition is a high or a 3.3 volts.
điều kiện idle, bit high, là ở 3.3 V
And then the data, when it wants to send,
khi cần gửi data
begins with a start bit which is low, which is always a level 0.
nó sẽ bắt đầu với bit low, là 0
And then the bits are sent 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
và các biết được gửi đi 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
And then we're going to have a stop bit.
sau đó ta có bit stop
And the stop bit is always high.
stop bit luôn ở trạng thái high
These 10 bits together are called a Frame.
10 bits này gộp lại thành 1 khung
And so in one Frame we see we have 10 total bits.
...
And encoded in those 10 total bits are eight data bits.
giải mã 10 bits này là data 8 bits
The other aspect of this serial communication
ta cần quan tâm 1 cái nữa
has to do with the time per bit.
là thời gian cho mỗi bit
The time per bit is called the bit-time.
gọi là bit-time
And one over the bit-time is called the baud-rate.
1 chia bit-time gọi là baud-rate
And that is the total number of bits transmitted per second.
đó là tổng số bit truyền đi trong 1 giây
As we saw in the last slide, the transmitter on the one computer
ở slide trước, ta nhớ, bộ phát của vi tính thì được kết nối vào bộ thu của vi tính khác
is connected up to the receiver on the other computer.
...
So this wave form here are the same on one side, the transmitter.
vậy, dãy này đây tượng trưng cho bộ phát
So these 10 bits are output from the transmitter and input to the receiver.
10 bits này là output từ bộ phát vào sẽ input vào bộ thu
So let's look at the transmitter.
giờ nhìn vào bộ phát
The transmitter has a 10-bit shift-register
nó có thanh ghi dịch chuyển 10-bit
which is connected to the transmit data output pin(TxD).
nó kết nồi vào pin(TxD)  output để chuyển data
There are 10 bits in here.
có 10 bit ở đây
The start bit will come out first and then bits 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
bit start ra trước, rồi tới 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
7 will come out next, and lastly the stop bit which you know is a one.
cuối cùng là bit stop, nó = 1
And these 10 bits are loaded into this shift-register.
10 bits sẽ được tài vào thanh ghi dịch chuyển
In order to make it happen the software will write to the data
để thực hiện việc trên, phần mềm phải ghi vào thanh ghi data
register so it's going to write to the data register.
...
And this data register has the name UART0.
thanh ghi data này có tên UART0
This number can be 0 through 7 data register (DR) underscore R,
nó có thể là thanh ghi data có số 0.....7
So it will write to this register.
nó sẽ ghi vào thanh ghi này
This 8 bits of data is then passed through a First In, First Out hardware
8 bit data này sẽ vào phần cứng Fisrt in, First out
FIFO and sent into this shift-register.
nó là FIFO, ta gửi data vào thanh ghi dịch chuyển này
DR RAMESH YERRABALLI: Does that mean that there is a buffer between the data
DR. YERRABALLI: nghĩa là có 1 bộ đệm giữa\ thanh ghi data và thanh ghi dịch chuyển
register that you write to and the shift-register that
thanh ghi dịch để gửi data ra ngoài
actually sends the data out?
...
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes, this is a 16 element buffer, or First In First
DR. JONATHAN: yes, đây là bộ đệm 16 elements hoặc gọi là First in First out queue
Out queue that allows the software to write many data into this buffer
nó cho phép phần mềm ghi data vào bộ đệm này
and then they're sent out one at a time.
và nó dược truyền ra 1 bit 1 thời điểm
There's one flag in this device that the software needs to know about.
có 1 flag ở thiết bị này mà phần mềm cần biết
And that is the transmit FIFO full flag(TXFF).
nó là bộ phát  FIFO full fag(TXFF)
And this flag is 1 if this FIFO is full and can't accept any more data.
flag = 1 nếu FIFO đầy và không thể nhét vào được nữa
And this flag is 0 so if it's not full and the software
flag = 0 nếu nó vẫn chưa đầy và phần mềm có thể ghi vào thanh ghi data
can write to the data register.
...
DR RAMESH YERRABALLI: Now, let's take a look
DR YERRABALLI: nhìn đây
at the receiver side of the transmission.
ở phía bộ thu, nó cũng như bộ phát
On the receiver side, just like the sender side,
...
there is a shift-register as well.
có thanh ghi dịch chuyển
This receiver shift-register is also of the same size, which is 10 bits.
thanh ghi này có cùng size = 10 bit
There is your start bit and the stop bit.
đây là start bit vào stop bit
And your payload, which is your data, which is 8 bits.
độ lớn của dữ liệu là 8 bits
Now when the software wants to read data it's
khi phần mềm muốn đọc data,
going to perform the read on the data register which we call UART0_DR_R.
nó sẽ đọc trên thanh ghi data, gọi là UART0_DR_R
And again, this 0 can be any number between 0 and 7 for the various UARTs.
số 0 này có là 0 ...7 cho từng loại UART
And we have a receiver FIFO which is also a 16-element buffer.
ta có bộ thu FIFO với bộ đệm 16-element
The receiver is slightly complicated compared to the sender in that
bộ thu thì khá phức tạp nếu so với bộ phát
when we receive data these 10 bits of data
khi ta nhận data, 10 bits này
are taken and converted to the 8 bits of payload.
data sẽ được chuyển thành payload 8 bits
So every element here will have the 8 bits of raw data and 4 other bits.
mỗi element ở đây đều có 8 bits cho data thô và 4 cho các bits khác
These 4 bits are for indicating errors.
4 bits này cho xác định lỗi
So we have what we call an overrun error bit(OE),
ta có bit overrun error (OE)
a break error bit(BE), a frame error bit(FE), and a parity error bit(PE).
a break error bit(BE), a frame error bit(FE), and a parity error bit(PE).
For now we will ignore the break error bit because we rarely use it.
ta sẽ bỏ qua bit break error, bởi vì ta hiếm khi xài
but we will talk about the overrun error bit.
nhưng ta sẽ tìm hiểu về bit error overrun
Remember that this is a 16 element buffer.
nên nhớ, đây là bộ đệm 16-element
So when data is being received, and if the sender is sending too fast,
khi data được nhân, và nếu bộ phát gửi quá nhanh
and if this buffer were to fill up, this receiver
nếu bộ đệm được xài hết,
will not have a place to put information.
bộ thu này se không có chỗ để đặt info
So the overrun error bit is set to 1 to indicate the buffer is full
bit error overrun được đổi thành 1 để chỉ bộ đếm đã đầy
and some frame had to be dropped.
và vài khung sẽ bị mất
So now, as far as a software is concerned
...
it's going to use a different flag which is the receive buffer RXFE flag
gio ta dùng 1 flag khác gọi là bộ đệm buffer RXFE flag (để nhận)
which is called the FIFO empty flag.
nó là FIFO empty flag
So what the receiver is going to do is it's
và bộ thu kiểm tra flag này nhiều lần
going to repeatedly check this flag.
...
And as long as this flag is a 0, which means that there's no data
khi flag này = 0, nghĩa là không có data để chứa
to be consumed, it keeps looping if it's trying to do a busy wait.
...
And when this becomes a 1 we know that there's at least some data here,
khi nó = 1, nghĩa là phải có 1 nhất 1 it data ở đây
so you can consume the data.
nên ta có thể tiêu thụ data
So the frame error is when this a Baud-rate mismatch, Baud-rate error,
error khung là khi có sự không phù hợp ở Baud-rate, Baud-rate error
which means that the sender and receiver have not
nghĩa là bộ phát và bộ thu không được chuẩn hóa với cùng Baud-rate
been configured with the same Baud-rate.
...
And the parity error is a thing of the past.
parity error là thứ của quá khứ
We no longer use it.
ta không xài nó nữa
It's just it's just there for continuity in the protocol.
nó chỉ nằm đây trong protocol